Boker Tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's daf דף daf is Chaf
Vav כ"ו Chaf Vav and we continue with the whole discussion about
the drinking of the water and the ability for merit to forestall
the punishment. So, and the Mishnah משנה Mishnah said that sometimes merit
can forestall it one or two or three years. And now we
continue with two dots about six lines from the top. So let's
continue. V'yesh zechus toleh gimmel shanim ויש זכות תולה ג' שנים, V'yesh
zechus toleh gimmel shanim, sometimes merit can forestall as much as three
years. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says: Zechus d'mai זכות דמאי? Zechus
d'mai? What type of merit will have that power to forestall that
long? Ileima zechus d'Torah אילימא זכות דתורה, Ileima zechus d'Torah, if it's
the zechus זכות zechus of learning Torah תורה, Torah, which is interesting
because later the Mishnah משנה Mishnah talks about learning Torah תורה Torah
either as a good thing so she'll understand if and why the
water didn't work, or as a bad thing that it'll give her
a way to
cheat the system. So here though the Gemara גמרא Gemara is maybe
picking up on that, and we'll see in a minute maybe why
that is, but the Gemara גמרא Gemara is saying that maybe it's
the merit of learning Torah תורה, Torah, if a woman learns Torah
תורה Torah maybe that has the merit of forestalling the punishment of
the Sotah סוטה. Sotah. So ileima zechus d'Torah אילימא זכות דתורה, Ileima
zechus d'Torah, ha einah metzuva v'osa הא אינה מצווה ועושה, ha einah
metzuva v'osa, but she's not commanded to learn Torah תורה, Torah, so
it doesn't imagine that the merit of that, even though it's obviously
the merit of Talmud Torah תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, but given that
it's an eina metzuva אינה מצווה eina metzuva type of a merit,
it would not be strong enough to forestall punishment. Ela zechus d'mitzvah
אלא זכות דמצוה, Ela zechus d'mitzvah, maybe it's other mitzvos מצוות mitzvos
that she does? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says: Zechus d'mitzvah mi
magna kulei hai זכות דמצוה מי מגנא כולי האי? Zechus d'mitzvah mi
magna kulei hai? Since when does mitzvah מצוה mitzvah have that type
of a power of protection from punishment? V'ha tanya והתניא, V'ha tanya,
we taught in a Braita ברייתא, Braita, edzu darash Rabi Menachem bar
Rabi Yosi אדזו דרש רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי, edzu darash Rabi Menachem
bar Rabi Yosi, this is what Rabi Menachem bar Rabi Yosi teaches,
and presumably nothing to do with Sotah סוטה, Sotah, a general Braita
ברייתא Braita about the power of Torah תורה Torah and the power
of mitzvah מצוה. mitzvah. Ki ner mitzvah v'Torah or כי נר מצוה
ותורה אור, Ki ner mitzvah v'Torah or, because a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah
is a candle and the Torah תורה Torah is light. So hatla
hakatuv es hamitzvah b'ner התלה הכתוב את המצוה בנר, hatla hakatuv es
hamitzvah b'ner, the verse made a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah dependent on a
candle, made it compared it to a candle, v'es haTorah b'or ואת
התורה באור. v'es haTorah b'or. Es hamitzvah b'ner lomar lach את המצוה
בנר לומר לך, Es hamitzvah b'ner lomar lach, to tell you, ma
ner einah megina ela lefi sha'ah מה נר אינה מגינה אלא לפי
שעה, ma ner einah megina ela lefi sha'ah, some have the girsa
גרסא girsa me'ira lefi sha'ah מאירה לפי שעה, me'ira lefi sha'ah, the
same way a candle only protects or only gives light for a
brief period of time, af mitzvah einah megina ela lefi sha'ah אף
מצוה אינה מגינה אלא לפי שעה. af mitzvah einah megina ela lefi
sha'ah. So a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah will only have the power to
protect for a brief period of time, so presumably not one, two,
or three years, which is what the Mishnah משנה Mishnah said.
Ela lefi sha'ah אלא לפי שעה. Ela lefi sha'ah. V'es haTorah
b'or lomar lach ואת התורה באור לומר לך, V'es haTorah b'or lomar
lach, ma or magin or me'ir l'olam מה אור מגין או מאיר
לעולם, ma or magin or me'ir l'olam, the same way light always
protects or gives
light, light just means the light of the world, like a light
that's always there. So what?
It's the idea of light.
The idea of light, right.
So af Torah megina l'olam אף תורה מגינה לעולם, af Torah megina
l'olam, Torah תורה Torah protects forever. V'omer ואומר, V'omer, and it says
so therefore for Torah תורה Torah we could understand that it would
have a strong power to forestall the punishment. But a mitzvah מצוה,
mitzvah, why does it have such a powerful protection?
You missed the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, you missed it.
It said that it's eina metzuva v'osa אינה מצווה ועושה.
eina metzuva v'osa. No, but there's a difference between limud l'asiyah לימוד
לעשייה limud l'asiyah and limud l'shma לימוד לשמה, limud l'shma, right? Who
cares if you're metzuva v'osa מצווה ועושה metzuva v'osa in terms of
the actual limud לימוד limud of Torah תורה? Torah?
The Gemara גמרא Gemara does not feel that the power of Talmud
Torah תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah does not come from it like a
hechsher mitzvah הכשר מצוה hechsher mitzvah to enable her to do a
mitzvah מצוה. mitzvah. If it was just seen as a way of
learning the halachos הלכות halachos of things she has to do, then
how could it be more powerful than the actual mitzvah מצוה mitzvah
itself? Then it's just wrapped up in the value of doing the
mitzvah מצוה. mitzvah. But the mitzvah מצוה, mitzvah, well but the Gemara
גמרא Gemara assumes that as a Torah l'shma תורה לשמה, Torah l'shma,
that will not that does not carry the same value if it's
eina metzuva v'osa אינה מצווה ועושה, eina metzuva v'osa, that's the Gemara's
גמרא Gemara assumption. Qua the mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of Talmud Torah תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah for an eina metzuva v'osa אינה מצווה ועושה, eina
metzuva v'osa, that does not carry the same value. Now it is
funny because the Gemara גמרא Gemara could have said that the power
of Torah תורה Torah is not coming from the power of the
s'char שכר s'char and the kiyum hamitzvah sheba קיום המצוה שבה, kiyum
hamitzvah sheba, the power of Torah תורה Torah is coming from the
actual value of the dvar Hashem sheba דבר השם שבה. dvar Hashem
sheba. It could have said that right, but it's interestingly not, at
least this Braita ברייתא Braita isn't denying that, but the stam סתם
stam of the Gemara גמרא Gemara that's challenging it is somehow assuming
that the protective power comes from the power of the value of
the kiyum hamitzvah קיום המצוה kiyum hamitzvah of Talmud Torah תלמוד תורה,
Talmud Torah, not from the value of the Torah תורה Torah itself.
You know it's an interesting like for example, this is going to
be relevant because of course we're going to lead into the whole
discussion about melamedes bito Torah, lamda tiflus מלמדה בתו תורה, למדה תפלות
melamedes bito Torah, lamda tiflus or whatever. You know that the Shulchan
Aruch שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch paskens פוסק paskens that women do not
say a bracha ברכה bracha on mitzvas asei shehazman grama מצוות עשה
שהזמן גרמא mitzvas asei shehazman grama if they were to take a
lulav לולב, lulav, but women do say a bracha ברכה bracha when
at birchas haTorah ברכות התורה birchas haTorah in the morning before learning
Torah תורה, Torah, they actually do say a
bracha ברכה. bracha. So like what's the logic? The Soloveitchik explains that's
not a bracha ברכה bracha on the mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of Torah
תורה, Torah, that's a bracha ברכה bracha on the cheftza חפצא cheftza
of Torah תורה. Torah. You know that's a bracha ברכה bracha which
is obviously true because a birchas hamitzvah ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah has
both elements: asher kishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu la'asok b'divrei Torah אשר קדשנו במצותיו
וצונו לעסוק בדברי תורה, asher kishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu la'asok b'divrei Torah, which
is sort of like the mitzvah מצוה, mitzvah, but then it also
has v'ha'arev na divrei והערב נא דברי v'ha'arev na divrei melamed Torah
l'amo Yisrael מלמד תורה לעמו ישראל melamed Torah l'amo Yisrael bocher asher
bachar banu בוחר אשר בחר בנו. bocher asher bachar banu. so I
mean נותן התורה, Nosen HaTorah, so it's about the power of תורה,
Torah, so he says that doesn't matter whether, you know, it's considered
like you're בגדר B'geder מצווה ועושה Metzuve V'ose or not. So you
definitely could have said that in terms of the protective power, I
agree with you, but the גמרא Gemara somehow is thinking that it
comes through the קיום Kiyum the power of the קיום Kiyum of
the
מצוה. Mitzva. Okay. ואומר V'omer and the verse says, בהתהלכך תנחה אותך
בשכבך תשמר עליך והקיצות היא תשיחך. Behishalchecha Tancha Osach Bishochbecha Tishmor Alecha
V'hakitzosa He Tisichecha. Anybody who's been doing דף יומי, Daf Yomi, that's
a פסוק Pasuk that should be familiar with. We say it like
once
every every like one to two months or so. Yeah, but it's
true. בהתהלכך תנחה אותך, Behishalchecha Tancha Osach, when you in your in
your walking it will lead you. זה לעולם הזה. Ze L'olam Hazeh.
So this is referring to the תורה, Torah, so the תורה Torah
will guide you in this world, right? It's not just a מצוה,
Mitzva, like תורה Torah guides you. It gives you direction. It tells
you what path to go on. Okay. זה לעולם הזה. Ze L'olam
Hazeh. בשכבך תשמור עליך, Bishochbecha Tishmor Alecha, when you sleep it will
guard you, זו מיתה. Zu Misah. It'll be there to protect you
even when you die. והקיצות היא תשיחך, V'hakitzosa He Tisichecha, and when
you wake up that will be your speech, לעתיד לבוא, L'asid Lavo,
in the future. So either that'll be the basis of your living
in תחיית המתים, Techiyas Hamaysim, or רש"י Rashi says when you get
up to heaven, the תורה Torah will sort of, you know, defend,
speak on your behalf, all the תורה Torah that you have learned.
So that is the power of תורה. Torah. It gives you guidance
in this world and it protects you in the future. Okay. משל
לאדם שהיה מהלך באישון לילה. Mashal L'adam Shehaya Mehalech B'ishon Layla. It's
comparable to a person who was going in the darkness of night
ואפילה, Va'afeila, it was like dark and you know and dark. Another
word
for that. ומתיירא מן הקוצים ומן הפחתים ומן הברקנים. U'misyarei Min Hakotzim
U'min Hapchatim U'min Habarkanim. And he was afraid from the thorns and
from the and from the pits and from the ברקנים, Barkanim, those
other type of thistles, I know it's not so much different from
the קוצים. Kotzim. Anyway, from all the stumbling things on the way.
ומחיה רעה ומן הליסטים. U'michaya Ra'ah U'min Halistim. And from the, you
know, wild animals and the bandits. ואינו יודע באיזה דרך מהלך. V'eino
Yodeia B'eizeh Derech Mehalech. And he also besides just about being attacked
and tripping and hurting himself, he doesn't know how to get himself,
what path to go on, how to get himself out of the
forest. נזדמנה לו אבוקה של אור. Nizdamna Lo Avuka Shel Or. He
chanced upon, I know maybe he pulled it out of the knapsack,
a
torch. ניצל מן הקוצים ומן הפחתים ומן הברקנים. Nitzal Min Hakotzim U'min
Hapchatim U'min Habarkanim. That helps him. He can see immediately in front
of him. So he's not going to trip on the thorns and
the thistles and the stumbling blocks and into the pits. Okay. ועדיין
מתיירא מחיה רעה ומן הליסטים. V'adayin Misyarei Michaya Ra'ah U'min Halistim. But
if that's not enough, I mean there's still all these evil animals,
you know, lurking outside and you know and all these bandits and
a torch isn't going to make the difference. ואינו יודע באיזה דרך
מהלך. V'eino Yodeia B'eizeh Derech Mehalech. And again he still doesn't know
which path to go on. He now well he's not in danger
but he doesn't know where he's going. כיון שעלה עמוד השחר. Keivan
She'ala Amud Hashachar. Once the morning star rises. ניצל מחיה רעה ומן
הליסטים. Nitzal Michaya Ra'ah U'min Halistim. Then it's day. That's אור. Or.
Okay. And with the אור Or these all these evils of night
fade away. So ועדיין אינו יודע באיזה דרך מהלך. V'adayin Eino Yodeia
B'eizeh Derech Mehalech. But he still doesn't know which path to go
on. He now well he's not in danger but he doesn't know
where he's going. הגיע לפרשת דרכים. Higa L'parshas Drachim. He comes to
a crossroads. Presumably there's some sign on the crossroads. Otherwise how would
that help? Anyway, ניצל מכולם. Nitzal Mikulam. Now he's saved. Now he
knows what path to go on. So it's not clear what this
פרשת דרכים Parshas Drachim is. Like we got it, like you know
the the immediate dangers was like the נר מצוה. Ner Mitzva. You
do a מצוה Mitzva and it protects you from like some some
immediate dangers. But it doesn't protect you like long term and doesn't
protect you from bigger dangers or whatever. That's the תורה אור. Torah
Or. That's daybreak. But what is this thing about finding the right
path? So the גמרא Gemara will...
that's לעתיד לבוא, L'asid Lavo, right? When you when you die, right?
Okay, maybe, maybe.
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim then it'll lead you to the right path
whether meaning גיהנום... Gehenom...
okay. So we'll see, that'll be one answer that the תורה Torah
got you all the way to that point. But it also sounds
like there was some other maybe it's just תחייה, Techiyah, it's nothing
new, it's just you've now it's led you through your entire life
and now you're saved. But maybe it's also some other thing is
going to help you at this stage and we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara.
But this function of this אגדתא Agadata is to do what? Say
that if she learns תורה... Torah...
no this אגדתא Agadata is not about women. This אגדתא Agadata is
just אגדתא Agadata about the power of תורה. Torah. נר מצוה ותורה
אור. Ner Mitzvah V'Torah Or. Well I'll tell you, you came a
minute late so I'll tell
you. נר מצוה ותורה אור. Ner Mitzvah V'Torah Or. The purpose of
this אגדתא Agadata is the power of תורה Torah compared to the
power of a מצוה. Mitzva. A מצוה Mitzva just saves you, protects
you like momentarily for a brief period of time. תורה Torah has
long-lasting protection. So the גמרא Gemara says what is the protection that
what is the merit that protects this woman for up to three
years from the punishment? It can't be a מצוה Mitzva because that's
only brief and momentary. But it can't be תורה Torah because she's
אינה מצווה ועושה. Eina Metzuvah V'osah. So how could it be? That
was what I was discussing with Michael a minute ago. How could
it be that the that her learning of תורה Torah if she
learned תורה Torah would have that type of a power if she
doesn't get the full merit that learning תורה Torah affords because she's
not מצווה Metzuvah in it.
But even if she had this אגדתא's Agadata I'm understanding suggest that
the power of תורה Torah is so universally built into the structure
of the world that it would that it makes it obviates the
fact that she's not מצווה. Metzuvah.
That's what you're saying, but that's not what the גמרא Gemara is
saying. The גמרא Gemara is quoting this אגדתא. Agadata. No, the גמרא—you
Gemara missed the opening line. The גמרא Gemara is quoting this אגדתא
Agadata and saying if it's תורה Torah she got, that doesn't have
its power for her. If it's מצוה, mitzvah, here's a whole אגדתא
Agadata that shows you that a מצוה mitzvah isn't strong enough to
protect her. So it's assuming that the power of the תורה Torah
here is not available to her in this degree because she's אינה
מצווה. eina metzuva. Now, you could say and Michael could say and
I could say, we could all say that even if she's not
מצווה metzuva and she doesn't get the merit for קיום המצוה kiyoom
hamitzvah of תורה, Torah, but the power of תורה Torah as דבר
השם Dvar Hashem and her connecting to that דבר השם, Dvar Hashem,
whatever מצוה mitzvah points she does or doesn't get, that has a
power to protect her, right? So that you could—that's—but for some reason
the גמרא Gemara is not saying that and it's basically saying at
this stage תורה—we'll Torah see how it's going to answer in the
end—תורה Torah does not ultimately afford her that type of protection if
she's not מצווה. metzuva. Okay.
One second, isn't she מצווה metzuva to learn the things she has
to learn?
That is not understood as a מצות תלמוד תורה. mitzvath talmud Torah.
That's understood as הכשר מצוה hechsher mitzvah for the things she has
to do. So if she—if keeping שבת Shabbos doesn't give her this
protection, how does learning the הלכות halachos of שבת, Shabbos, which is
just enabling her to keep שבת, Shabbos, give her more protection than
the keeping of שבת Shabbos itself?
Okay, so now the גמרא—so Gemara we still don't understand what it
is that is protecting her. Okay, so it says like
this: דבר אחר. davar acher. עבירה מכבה מצוה. avera mechaba mitzvah. An
עבירה avera can extinguish a מצוה. mitzvah. So that presumably means extinguish
the—it might mean extinguish the protection of a מצוה, mitzvah, which would
mean—well we're going back of course to the light imagery—can extinguish a
מצוה. mitzvah. Where were we? מכבה מצוה. mechaba mitzvah. ואין עבירה מכבה
תורה, ve'ein avera mechaba Torah, cannot extinguish the תורה. Torah. So it
could mean the protection, but then it would be going against, you
know, the point about that the מצוה mitzvah affords—affords protection. So maybe
it only affords protection in the absence of עבירות. averos. But if
we think that the protection means protection from being punished for your
sins and מצוות mitzvos at least give that—give it for a brief
period of time, not a long period of time, what does it
mean that the עבירה avera extinguishes the מצוה? mitzvah? So רש"י Rashi
says extinguishes doesn't mean the protection of the מצוה, mitzvah, but it
extinguishes the—the reward of the מצוה. mitzvah. You've done some מצוות, mitzvos,
you've done some עבירות. averos. לעתיד לבוא, le'atid lavo, they might cancel
themselves out. I mean it's one thing that the מצוה mitzvah might
have the ability to a little bit forestall punishment for a brief
period of time, but ultimately it will cancel—might be cancelled out by
עבירות. averos. But עבירות averos will not cancel out תורה. Torah. שנאמר:
shene'emar: מים רבים לא יוכלו לכבות את האהבה. mayim rabim lo yuchlu
lechabot et ha'ahava. Great waters cannot extinguish the love. And the love
here obviously talking about love of תורה. Torah. And of course it's
interesting because as the מהרש"א Maharsha points out, sometimes of course תורה
Torah is compared to מים, mayim, but here תורה Torah is a
fire, right? It's a נר, ner, it's an אור. or. It's these
light types of things. So the water here is the עבירות averos
and ultimately therefore anyway תורה Torah is a lasting, long, you know,
all-encompassing protection that cannot be extinguished. מצוות mitzvos is only brief and
momentary. So we cannot understand that the מצוה mitzvah would protect her
for a long period of time, certainly not up to three years,
and we can't understand that the תורה Torah would do this if
she's not מצווה ועושה. metzuva v'osa. So we have a—so—so we're stuck.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. אמר
רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So says
רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: מצוה בעידנא דעסיק בה מגנה ומצלה. Mitzvah b'idna
d'asik bah megana u'matzla. Here's how it works. מצוה mitzvah while you're
doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're giving—something to the poor, you're keeping שבת,
Shabbos, you're taking the לולב, lulav, you're sitting in a סוכה. sukkah.
While you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah, so—so מגנה ומצלה. megana u'matzla. It
protects you from punishment and מצלה matzla here is understood, as we'll
see in a minute in the גמרא, Gemara, רש"י Rashi says it
here but it's based on the next גמרא, Gemara, it protects you
from doing a sin. So it protects you from—from punishment for the
past and while you're doing a מצוה mitzvah you're not—you know, you're—you're
being protected from actually right now being tempted into sin. בעידנא דלא
עסיק בה, B'idna d'lo asik bah, but when you stop, as soon
as you stop doing the מצוה, mitzvah, אגוני מגני, aguni magnei, it
still—it still has protective powers, okay, but אצולי לא מצלה, atzulei lo
matzla, but it doesn't protect you from sinning. תורה—so Torah then—so actually
he's saying look, מצוה, mitzvah, its weakness is the ability to have—protect
you from straying, from sinning in the future. But actually it does
forestall punishment, you know, it does protect you from sin. So that's
why it's protected סוטה Sotah from being punished, this woman from being
punished, okay? And the difference is that תורה Torah has the ability
not only to—to forestall punishment but to protect you from sinning in
the future. Okay.
Where are we? תורה בין בעידנא דעסיק בה ובין בעידנא דלא עסיק
בה. Torah bein b'idna d'asik bah u'vein b'idna d'lo asik bah. תורה
Torah whether you're learning תורה Torah or not learning תורה, Torah, מגנה
ומצלה. megana u'matzla. Not only does it forestall punishment but it protects
you from sinning. But it also saves you from sinning, which makes
sense right about how תורה Torah should shape character and elevate you
and set you more on a right path and so on, it's
the power of education as opposed to just doing some ritual.
What if it's actually someone who learns תורה Torah with regularity? In
other words, you can't learn תורה Torah once and then ten years
go by?
Yeah,
right, that's a good question too. Right, I don't know.
And then there's
the question of לשמה lishma or שלא לשמה? shelo lishma? Yeah, all
right, good, we can figure it all out. Anyway, right now, the
basic answer is maybe a מצוה mitzvah does protect, forestall punishment. And
the difference between it and תורה Torah is how much it keeps
you from sinning. So the גמרא Gemara says,
even forestall punishment for three years then?
Yeah, forestall for even, we even work up to three years. That's
our current answer. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רבא matkif
lah Rava or רבא Rava asked, or רבא Rava asked on this
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if
that's true, דואג ואחיתופל, Doeg va'Achitofel, how about דואג ואחיתופל Doeg va'Achitofel
who basically sinned and attacked דוד David and they in rabbinic literature
were like big תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. So מי לא עסקי בתורה,
mi lo askei beTorah, they learned תורה, Torah, אמאי לא הגינה עלייהו,
amai lo higina aleihu, why did it not actually, should be according
to this מצלא עלייהו matzla aleihu anyway, why didn't it stop them
from sinning? Because there are plenty, there are people who learn תורה
Torah and they go off the דורך derech and they sin, so
you can't say that תורה Torah always protects you from sinning in
the future. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather says רבא,
Rava, תורה, Torah,
here's how we're going to make the split and still get מצוה
mitzvah protecting this woman from punishment. תורה Torah בעידנא דעסיק בה, be'idna
de'asik bah, when you're learning תורה, Torah, מגנא ומצלא, magna umatzla,
it protects you from punishment notice you're also עסיק בה asik bah
it protects you from punishment and it saves you from sin. בעידנא
דלא עסיק בה, be'idna delo asik bah, when you're not learning תורה,
Torah, אגוני מגנא, aguni magna, it can still forestall punishment, אצולי לא
מצלא, atzulei lo matzla, but it won't necessarily stop you from sinning.
A person could learn תורה Torah and then go ahead and sin
after they leave the בית מדרש. beit midrash. Okay, but it'll still
protect you when you're not immediately learning. מצוה, mitzvah, a מצוה, mitzvah,
בין בעידנא דעסיק בה בין בעידנא
דלא עסיק בה, bein be'idna de'asik bah bein be'idna delo asik bah,
whether you're doing a מצוה mitzvah or not, אגוני מגנא, aguni magna,
that will protect you, so it'll protect you even after you're done
doing it, אצולי לא מצלא, atzulei lo matzla, but even while you're
doing a מצוה, mitzvah, that's not going to have the power to
stop you from sinning, which is interesting. Like, I don't know, it'd
be pretty hypocritical, but I mean if you think about it on
the other hand, talk about like something like the משנה ברורה Mishnah
Berurah says, while you're sitting in a סוכה sukkah you should not
be talking לשון הרע. lashon hara. So
it's possible, he says you should never talk לשון הרע, lashon hara,
but how can you be thinking about doing it while you're sitting
in a סוכה? sukkah? So I guess it's possible to be doing
מצוות mitzvot and at the same time be sinning. But it's also
possible to learn תורה Torah and at the same time be sinning,
but okay, the גמרא Gemara assumes lest so. So right now we're
trying to construct an answer that explains that מצוות mitzvot can protect
after you're done doing them and still explains the additional, but what's
the additional power of תורה? Torah? So we can't say the additional
power of תורה Torah is stopping you from sinning after you're no
longer learning, we see that's not true. So what it says is
both מצוות mitzvot and תורה Torah protect you after you're done and
therefore a מצוה mitzvah could protect this woman after she's done. תורה
Torah has the additional power of while you're learning תורה, Torah, stopping
you from sinning in the future. Now that doesn't work so well
with all the lovely metaphors before in the גמרא, Gemara, it sounded
like it was more than just the power to stop you from
sinning while you're actually learning. But anyway, that's how the גמרא's Gemara
now constructed this difference to explain how the מצוה mitzvah could forestall
punishment for this woman. We're going to have better answers from other
answers. Okay, רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says, I mean I
think again for all of us the best answer would have been
she's אינה מצווה ועושה, eina metzuva ve'osa, but the תורה Torah still
protects her, but let's see what רבינא Ravina says. רבינא אמר, Ravina
amar, לעולם זכות תורה, le'olam zechut Torah, it is the merit of
תורה Torah that protects this woman. ודקאמרת אינה מצווה ועושה, vedeka'amrat eina
metzuva ve'osa, you were bothered she's אינה מצווה ועושה, eina metzuva ve'osa,
so how could it have sort of protective powers for her?
אינה מצווה ועושה, eina metzuva ve'osa, ניהי דפקודי לא מיפקדא, nihi depikudei
lo mifkada, it's true she's not commanded, באגרא, be'agra, but in the
reward, in the merit, in the זכות, zechut, דמקרין ומתניין בנייהו, demakrin
umatnyan bnaihu, that they cause their kids to, מקרין makrin is like
read פסוקים, pesukim, right?
And אגרא, agra, right? שכר, sechar, right?
שכר, sechar, שכר, sechar, I see, get it right? Oh yeah, שכר,
sechar, yeah. באגרא דמקרין ומתניין בנייהו, be'agra demakrin umatnyan bnaihu, that they
have their kids read, learn מקרא Mikra and learn משנה, Mishnah, basically
they wake up their kids and send them off to school and,
no, not well could be, but it doesn't sound like it. Okay,
the fact that they basically ensure their kids make it to חדר,
cheder, ונטרין להו לגברייהו עד דאתו מבי מדרשא, unatrin lehu legavreihu ad
de'atu mibei midrasha, and they basically patiently wait for their husbands to
return from the study hall and they keep the house nice and
clean and they make the meals or whatever, and they enable, so
they're enablers basically,
the woman as the כלי, kli, the woman as the enabler, she
enables not in a bad way, in a good way, enabling something
good, she enables her children to go and to her boy children
to go and to learn תורה, Torah, she enables her husband to
go and to learn תורה. Torah. Exactly. So ונטרין לגברייהו עד דאתו
מבי מדרשא
unatrin legavreihu ad
de'atu mibei
midrasha מבי מדרשא מי לא
פלגא בהדייהו? mi-bei midrasha mi lo palga bahadayhu? So of a get
a חלק chelek in that reward. So if they learned their own
תורה, Torah, it would only, it would be women's תורה, Torah, it
would be not of the same level, it would be אינו מצווה
ועושה. eino metzuve ve'oseh. But if they enable men's תורה, Torah, then
they get a portion in the man's תורה, Torah, they're part of
the man's מצווה ועושה, metzuve ve'oseh, and that is what protects them.
So there you go. Not a, not a גמרא Gemara that necessarily
fits with our contemporary, contemporary sensibilities. It reminds me of this great
line many years ago, decades ago when my wife דבורה Devorah was
learning in דרישה Drisha for like the first time and, and she
was learning with, you know, it was like this cadre of women
that like for the first time in their lives were learning תורה.
Torah. This is when women learning גמרא Gemara was still pretty new,
anyway. So she had this חברותא chavrusa who said to her like
after like a while she said, wait, wait, she said, I finally
got the system figured out. She said,
men are Jews, boys are future Jews, women are producers of Jews.
So there you go. Men learn תורה, Torah, boys learn תורה Torah
that actually counts. Even the kids are under בר מצווה, bar mitzvah,
their תורה Torah still more in the גדר geder of male תורה
Torah because eventually they'll be men learning תורה. Torah. And the women
get the merit for enabling all of that to happen.
Yes, I point out as that, I mean just the way this
is sort of, the picture I have in my mind is the
counterpoint that we had before, the סוטה sotah should be waiting for
her paramour, right? Right, this righteous woman, the גמרא Gemara says she's
waiting for her husband
to come home from learning תורה.
Torah. So I think in some ways it's a contrast to what
we said before.
That is true. And the גמרא Gemara that says before that when
a woman commits adultery, like the whole house falls apart because she's
not attending to the needs of the house. And here, this woman
who eventually was accused of being a סוטה, sotah, and maybe actually
committed adultery because it's זכות התורה תולה לה, zechus ha-Torah toulah lah,
so she did commit adultery, but the merit is actually about how
much she actually provided a home for, for learning and so on.
Right. But it is, I understand, but anyway, especially in the later
משנה mishnah that says לעולם ילמד אדם את בתו תורה, le-olam yilamed
adam es bito Torah, right, it is like one does wonder how
much, right, there's always like the question of like what exactly the,
you know, agenda of the סתם. stam. Does he somehow have an
agenda, is it just figuring things out? Right, there's nothing that forced
the גמרא Gemara to go in this direction, right, as we all
said, you know, first of all, if you think about it, we
ended yesterday by quoting that merit suspends for three years by נבוכדנצר.
Nevuchadnezzar. You know what נבוכדנצר's Nevuchadnezzar merit was? He gave money to
the poor. So there was nothing that forced the גמרא Gemara to
quote this ברייתא, braisa, to make it central, to refuse to be
able to accept the idea that a normal מצווה mitzvah could have
this merit, to refuse to be able to accept the idea that
תורה Torah of an אינו מצווה ועושה eino metzuve ve'oseh wouldn't have
the merit. Right, like it didn't have to go down this path
for many reasons, right, but one does wonder given the later part
of the משנה mishnah which talks about, you know, לעולם ילמד אדם
את בתו תורה, le-olam yilamed adam es bito Torah, you know, this
גמרא Gemara coming right before that or right in that context is
actually counterbalancing that message besides the fact that, you know, רבי, Rebbi,
who has it, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer himself already counterbalances that message
as רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and says, רבי אליעזר אומר כל המלמד
את בתו תורה כאילו מלמדה תפלות. Rabbi Eliezer omer kol hamelamed es
bito Torah ke'ilu melamdah tiflus. Right, the גמרא Gemara here is already
saying whatever merit a woman gets for learning תורה, Torah, it's really
not intrinsic merit. The real merit is enabling men learning תורה. Torah.
So it's very interesting given the context that the גמרא, Gemara, you
know, is choosing to bring this up right here, frame the issues
this way. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara goes back so to
this, to this, to this idea that the תורה Torah got you
sort of, you know, protected you from the bandits and the, and
the wild animals, but then you when you came to the crossroads,
then you finally knew which path to go on, which of course
is that famous Yogi Berra line which is, when you come to
a fork in the road, take it. Right? So anyway, what could
the פרשת דרכים parashas drachim be if you don't know which way
you're supposed to go on the פרשת דרכים? parashas drachim? Anyway, so
let's see what this פרשת דרכים parashas drachim is, which you finally
now know the right way to go. מאי פרשת דרכים? mai parashas
drachim? So מאי פרשת דרכים, mai parashas drachim, what is the crossroads?
אמר רב חסדא זו תלמיד חכם ויום המיתה. amar Rav Chisda zu
talmid chacham ve-yom ha-misa. Ah, Mike, what you said, it's basically, no,
the תורה Torah leads you through your life and the crossroads is
basically when you're departing your life and going into the next life.
And when you're dying, and if the תורה Torah got you that
far, meaning you don't know which path you'll go on, means like
אל תאמין בעצמך עד יום מותך. al ta'amin be-atzmecha ad yom mosecha.
The תורה Torah is protecting you, it's leading you, but ultimately you
don't know, are you destined for עולם הבא olam ha-ba or not
destined for עולם הבא? olam ha-ba? Will it be there, will you
be able to stay on the right path till the very end?
When you get to פרשת דרכים, parashas drachim, like the crossroads, right,
when you get to actually now leaving this life and to the
next world, now you know that the תורה Torah has protected you
and kept you on the right path right till the very end
and set you on the path for עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. Okay.
So what about the תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham?
What does he have to do with it? I mean just the
way this is sort of, תלמיד חכם talmid chacham means no, somebody's
learned תורה Torah and פרשת דרכים parashas drachim is יום המיתה. yom
ha-misa. You've gotten, you've gotten all the way till, till you know...
I would have thought it'd be more like maybe צדיק, tzaddik, you
know what I mean?
No, no, no, it's all about learning
תורה, Torah, like a big sinner, you know?
But but the point though is that no, the תורה Torah did
keep you on the right path. There's that presumption. The תורה Torah
has been keeping... keeping you on the path all the way till
that fateful day, till the פרשת דרכים. parshas drachim. But רב יצחק
אמר, Rav Yitzchak amar, no, זה תלמיד חכם ביראת חטא, zeh talmid
chacham b'yirat chet,
there you go Michael, which is: No, no, no, no, no. Wait,
wait. תורה Torah can't do everything. תורה Torah can teach you what's
right and wrong. It can't actually make you make the right choices.
Ultimately, you need to bring to that a sense of fear of
sin, of righteousness. So the תורה Torah has lit up the world
for you, it's the אור. or. You now know how you're going
to—ראה נתתי לפניך היום את החיים ואת הטוב ואת המות ואת הרע.
re'eh nasati lefanecha hayom et hachayim v'et hatov v'et hamavet v'et hara.
You now know what's the right path, but you don't know which
path you're going to go on. You don't know are you going
to choose the right path. You know what it is, but will
you choose it? So that's ultimately you're at the פרשת דרכים. parshas
drachim. Which path will you choose? And you need the יראת חטא
yirat chet to help you choose the right path. That's a nice
metaphor.
Is it fear of heaven or יראת שמים?
yirat shamayim? Well, that too. But here we're talking exactly about the
various qualities you need. מר זוטרא אמר: Mar Zutra amar: זה תלמיד
חכם דסלקא שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא. zeh talmid chacham d'sakla shma'ta aliba d'hilchasa.
Now, basically, תורה Torah is good, but ultimately you don't know if
your learning תורה Torah will lead you to conclude the right הלכה.
halacha. So here he's again bracketing the—he's assuming you'll make the—you know,
that you'll have the character to choose rightly, correctly, but you know,
תורה Torah itself doesn't fully light things up for you, right? So
תורה Torah itself, you know, because
it protects you from these bad stuff, but to ultimately show you
the right path, you have to translate your תורה Torah into the
bottom line הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh and come to the right conclusions.
Yes.
Eliyahu, do you see—do you see these three different positions forms for
me a kind of continuum from the mystical to the rational? In
other words, does the תורה Torah have a kind of mystical protective
power that's intrinsic to it, right? Or actually, amen, does it give
you sort of guidelines but you have to bring your rational sense
of reason?
I completely agree.
So it's very interesting, it goes from the sacramental to the rational.
Right. And also that the power of
תורה—the Torah last two are that the power of תורה Torah is
not all-encompassing, it actually cuts away a little into the דרשה. drasha.
Because the first one is: Well, תורה Torah might teach—might educate you,
but it doesn't necessarily, you know, make sure you make the right
choices, which you could say no, תורה Torah shapes your character and
will make—you know, will give you that יראת חטא. yirat chet. This
acknowledges that's not always true. You can be a big תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and not have the right character. The next one goes
even further and says: תורה Torah doesn't even always show you the
right choices, right? You know, you can learn תורה Torah but not
come to the right הלכה halachic conclusion. So sometimes, you know, so
each one of these actually a little
bit pulls—the first one is: תורה Torah does everything. You just have
to stick with it till you die. The other stuff is: תורה
Torah doesn't do it all by itself.
So that's also part of it.
Okay. So...
What you think might be a מצוה mitzvah might not really be
a מצוה. mitzvah.
Is that what you're saying? Yeah, you can learn תורה Torah and
you'll get merit of learning תורה, Torah, but if you learn—you know,
if you weren't אסיקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא, asukei shma'ta aliba d'hilchasa, you
could go ahead and act wrongly because you misunderstood what you were
learning, you didn't conclude properly. You see, Michael, that's this—that's your by-line,
every time we're learning a דף יומי, Daf Yomi, it's: What's the
הלכה? halacha? You want to be אסיקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא, asukei shma'ta
aliba d'hilchasa, I just want to learn תורה, Torah, so anyway. All
right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: דבר אחר, davar acher,
עבירה מכבה מצוה ואין עבירה מכבה תורה. averah m'chabeh mitzvah v'ein averah
m'chabeh Torah. So now we're going to analyze this. אמר רב יוסף:
Amar Rav Yosef: דרש רבי מנחם ברבי יוסף להאי קרא כסיני. darsha
Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yosef l'hai kra k'Sinai. רבי מנחם ברבי יוסף
Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yosef explained the following פסוק pasuk like סיני,
Sinai, like סיני, Sinai, like it was—like it was coming straight from
סיני. Sinai. ואם תאמר דרשו דואג ואחיתופל הכי, v'im tomar darshu Doeg
v'Achitophel hachi, and דואג ואחיתופל Doeg and Achitophel dinned around to hear
this דרשה drasha or understood this פסוק pasuk just as well. Of
course, as the מהרש"א Maharsha says, it's a פסוק pasuk
from—we're going to be looking at a פסוק pasuk from like שיר
השירים. Shir HaShirim. So they couldn't have דרשו darshened this פסוק pasuk
because it hadn't been written yet. But okay, it doesn't matter. Had
they understood this message this way—no, the גמרא's Gemara saying this way.
Had they understood the message of what רבי מנחם ברבי יוסף Rabbi
Menachem bar Rabbi Yosef learns from this פסוק, pasuk, לא רדפו בתר
דוד, lo radfu batar Dovid, they would not have attacked דוד. Dovid.
What was the message? דכתיב: dech'tiv:
לאמר אלהים עזבו, leimor Elohim azavo, to say that they had abandoned
God. So basically, this means דואג ואחיתופל Doeg and Achitophel figured, look,
דוד Dovid sinned, he committed adultery. Notice, by the way, also we're
reintroducing adultery now, except by the man. Okay. דוד Dovid committed adultery,
so it's proper to go ahead and attack him. He abandoned God.
So מאי דרש? mai darash? ולא יראה בך ערות דבר ושב מאחריך.
v'lo yeira'eh becha ervat davar v'shav me'achareicha. If you have a sin
of adultery—of nakedness, of forbidden sex, God will retreat from you. So
they figured דוד Dovid committed
adultery, he's now susceptible to attack. We can go ahead and attack
him. והן אינם יודעים, v'hein einam yodim, they did not realize, שעבירה
מכבה מצוה, she'averah m'chabeh mitzvah, it might be true that a sin
will extinguish the protection of a מצוה, mitzvah, but ואין עבירה מכבה
תורה, v'ein averah m'chabeh Torah, will not extinguish the protection of תורה.
Torah.
Mai—God will not forsake דוד Dovid because of דוד's Dovid תורה. Torah.
He might—if he had just had מצוות mitzvos it would be one
thing, but because דוד Dovid was also a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and a תורה... Torah... God did not forsake him. Which again, you
know, you have the flip. Here's a man's sexual sin continuing to
be protected, presumably the woman's sexual sin, she should continue to be
protected, but again, somehow relating to the context of תורה Torah not
just מצוה. mitzvah. מה בוז יבוזו לו? Mai boz yavozu lo? What
does the פסוק pasuk mean by שיר השירים Shir Hashirim אם יתן
איש את כל הון ביתו באהבה בוז יבוזו לו? im yitein ish
es kol hon beiso b'ahavah boz yavozu lo? So because of the
אהבה, ahavah, מים רבים לא יוכלו לכבות את האהבה. mayim rabim lo
yuchlu lachabos es ha'ahavah. So they will actually like, you know, people
will denigrate him if he you know, if he gives up all
of his home for for love. אמר עולא: Amar Ulla: לא כשמעון
אחי עזריה, lo k'Shimon achi Azarya, ולא כרבי יוחנן דבי נשיאה. v'lo
k'Rabbi Yochanan d'bei nesi'ah. You should not not like שמעון Shimon the
brother of עזריה Azarya or רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan from the נשיא's
Nasi's house. Meaning what? These were people that learned תורה, Torah, but
they learned תורה Torah because שמעון's Shimon's brother supported him. That's why
he was called אחי עזריה. Achi Azarya. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
learned תורה Torah because he was supported by the נשיא's Nasi's house.
So they weren't willing to sacrifice all for it. They needed to
maintain their level of you know, their their standard of living and
they they got contributions in order to enable that. So that was
okay, that's good, but that's not the that's not the highest level.
אלא כהלל ושבנא, Ella k'Hillel v'Shevna, but like הלל Hillel and his
brother שבנא. Shevna. Bet you didn't know that הלל Hillel had a
brother called שבנא. Shevna. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר, d'chi asa Rav
Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came he said הלל ושבנא
אחי הוו, Hillel v'Shevna achi havu, הלל Hillel and שבנא Shevna were
brothers. הלל עסק בתורה, Hillel asak b'Torah, הלל Hillel learned תורה. Torah.
שבנא עבד עסקא, Shevna avad iska, שבנא Shevna did business. לסוף אמר
ליה, L'sof amar lei, then שבנא Shevna said to him תא נערוב
וניפלוג, ta na'arov v'niflog, you know what? Let's let's go into a
whole you know, יששכר זבולון Yissachar Zevulun deal. Let's I'll give you
half of my earnings and you give me half of your תורה
Torah reward. So יצתה בת קול ואמרה: yatzta bas kol v'amrah: אם
יתן איש את כל הון ביתו באהבה בוז יבוזו לו. im yitein
ish es kol hon beiso b'ahavah boz yavozu lo. No, he was
willing to go ahead and and give up everything. He did not
want to give up you know, he did not want to trade
anything for his תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. He was willing to give
up all material gain, even people that were willing to support him,
that his תורה Torah should like just be his. And that sort
of so that would be like you know, the ideal.
So the idea in that פסוק pasuk in שיר השירים Shir Hashirim
is somebody who ameliorates his love or gives up some love in
order for a for material gain.
And הלל Hillel doesn't want to give up, yeah תורה, Torah, he
won't sell his תורה Torah for anything. Right. Alright. Alright. And so
keeping with the theme of תורה, Torah, we now turn to the
עמוד ב.
amud beis. Funny name, that שבנא. Shevna.
I don't know. Okay. So
אומר בן עזאי חייב אדם ללמד את בתו תורה, omer Ben Azzai
chayav adam l'lammed es bito Torah, a person is required to teach
his daughter תורה. Torah. Now of course it's a little bit like
you know, there's like a little like double message here because the
משנה Mishnah says you're חייב chayav to teach your daughter תורה, Torah,
so if the waters don't work she'll understand or she won't sort
of you know, question their efficacy. But now it seems like wait
a minute, but if you teach your daughter תורה, Torah, won't that
actually maybe also be the basis for her to be protected by
it? You know, which is sort of what the גמרא Gemara has
sort of introduced right in the previous discussion. Which leads into רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's concern that if you're מלמד את בתו תורה כאילו
מלמדה תפלות, melammed es bito Torah k'ilu melamdah tiflus, because learning תורה
Torah might actually be the basis to allow her to sin. So
is the תורה Torah for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the basis to
allow her to sin because it because you know, it protects her
from the punishment? Or is it the basis to allow her to
sin because it actually, you know, she just learns the loopholes? Once
she learns the laws and she learns the loopholes, before she didn't
realize that there's a loophole, now she'll learn the loophole and she'll
find out figure out a way to get around it. Or the
third thing is just learning תורה Torah in general, you know, makes
her more of a nuanced, subtle, crafty type of a thinker and
you know, gives her the כלים keilim to figure out how to
get around things. Okay, like you know, people something will
happen, she'll
drink, she would not be subject to punishment.
Right. And that's the problem. Right. So you know, you learn a
lot of תורה, Torah, you learn to split hairs. So last night
we were going to an event and we parked on the on
the you know, on the street and the sign said
like parking 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. Monday through Thursday, what is
it like? Licensed vehicles only, you know, official vehicles only. Then underneath
it said NYP license holders only. So we're doing like a whole
רש"י ותוספות. Rashi v'Tosafos. Is the NYP license holder only during the
7 to 7 hours or is that like a separate דין din
and even if you're not during the 7 to 7 it's always?
So like that's what happens. You learn too much תורה, Torah, you
have everything you sort of figure out all these distinctions. Anyway. Okay.
So the car was there, we didn't have a ticket. So all
the חכמים chachamim decided that it was the same. It was a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of licensed vehicles. Anyway. Okay. תפלות סלקא דעתך?
Tiflus salka daitach? So the גמרא Gemara okay. רבי אליעזר אומר כל
המלמד בתו תורה מלמדה תפלות. Rabbi Eliezer omer kol hamelammed bito Torah
melamdah tiflus.
So actually the גרסא girsa in the משנה Mishnah is you teach
her תפלות. tiflus. By the way, in terms of what does תפלות
tiflus mean? It seems very clear because it contrasted in the משנה,
Mishnah, a, the context of sexual sin, b, it contrasted to פרישות,
perishus, seems very clear it's about sexual sin. I did a little
bit of a look and you know, like one one place it's
not exactly about sexual sin, like one place it sort of talks
about like דברי שטות ותפלות, divrei shtus v'tiflus,
which is not clear whether. or it's something similar to שטות, shtus,
but it could be like sexual types
of banter. But another place it also speaks like about when בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael were complaining about the מן, mahn, and it says
שתפלו על המן, she-taflu al ha-mahn, שדיברו דברי תפלות, she-dibru divrei tiflus,
או שתפלו על המן, o she-taflu al ha-mahn,
which clearly is not sexual sin; it's clearly some type of derogatory
speech. On the other hand, other places clearly it's about sexual issues.
It speaks about why women and slaves cannot be in a זימון
zimmun together and it says משום תפלות. mishum tiflus. So presumably it
doesn't just mean that they're going to be talking about the ballgames
or something, you know, presumably it has something sexual. Or another good
example is it's talking when it's talking
about actually a different המן, Haman, about אחשורוש'ס סעודה, Achashverosh's seudah, it
says, you know, for the way of like בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
is that when they get together, they talk דברי תורה, divrei Torah,
but the way of like רשעים reshaim or whatever is when they
get together they talk דברי תפלות. divrei tiflus. And so it was
with אחשורוש. Achashverosh. They were all there at the
סעודה seudah and, you know, these officers were saying
the מדיות Madiyos have the most beautiful women and the other said
the פרסיות Parsiyos have the most beautiful women and this has the
most beautiful women, and he says, oh, none of you have seen
my wife ושתי, Vashti, etc. So clearly there it's talk around sexual
matters. So anyway, it definitely seems that even though it might sometimes
just mean like, you know, negative talk or disrespectful talk, it really
very often has the specific context of talk relating to sexual issues
or just in general sexual issues. So therefore, that's what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says. So the גמרא Gemara says תפלות סלקא דעתך? tiflus
salka deitach? You really think that תורה Torah is תפלות? tiflus? You're
teaching her תפלות? tiflus? That's what תורה Torah is? So אלא אימא
כאילו למדה תפלות. ela eima ke'ilu limda tiflus. It's like you taught
her תפלות. tiflus. Obviously, it's not. תורה's Torah תורה, Torah, but it's
the same effect of teaching her that because again, it teaches her
to be crafty, it teaches her what the loopholes are in this
particular area of
הלכה, halacha,
etc. And אמר רבי אבהו מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? amar Rabbi Abbahu
mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? What's the reason of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer?
דכתיב אני חכמה שכנתי ערמה, d'ksiv ani chochma shakanti arma, I am
wisdom, I have dwelt with craftiness. כיון שנכנס חכמה באדם נכנסה עמו
ערמומית. keivan she-nichnas chochma b'adam nichnesa imo armumis.
Once wisdom goes into a person, they develop, you know, more subtlety
and craftiness. So of course the question is, and what about men?
So again, it's an interesting question. Does it mean that, well, men,
you can't help it, like they're already learning, so, you know, they
have a מצוה mitzvah to learn, you gotta deal with it? Or
does it mean somehow, no, we trust men with that type of,
you know, we with that ability more than we trust women? So
I mean, so that's not exactly clear exactly how it deals with
that issue for men. ורבנן, v'rabanan, what do the rabbis say who
say it's not a problem to teach a daughter תורה Torah and
maybe you should teach her תורה? Torah? האי אני חכמה מאי עבדי
ליה? hai ani chochma mai avdi lei? What do they do with
that? מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוסי בר חנינא. mibaei lei l'che'd'Rabbi Yosi bar
Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא אין דברי תורה מתקיימין אלא במי
שמעמיד עצמו ערום
עליהן. d'amar Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina ein divrei Torah miskaymin ela b'mi
she-ma'amid atzmo arom aleihen. So ערמה arma here is not craftiness, but
naked. If you're willing, like we said before, like to give up
everything, you know, make yourself naked, not pursue any, you know, any
pleasures or whatever and just to devote yourself a hundred and ten
percent to learning תורה, Torah, that is the way you'll learn תורה.
Torah. שנאמר אני חכמה שכנתי ערמה. she-ne'emar ani chochma shakanti arma. אמר
רבי יוחנן אין דברי תורה מתקיימין אלא במי שמשים עצמו כמי שאינו.
amar Rabbi Yochanan ein divrei Torah miskaymin ela b'mi she-mesim atzmo k'mi
she-eino. Oh, תורה Torah is... anyway, רש"י Rashi I think says זו
ערמה. zo arma. I read it as naked, but רש"י Rashi says
לשון אחר שמשים עצמו ערום עליהן שמערימין שיתקיים תורתה ליפוץ יד לימלוכה
דאדם. lashon acher she-mesim atzmo arom aleihen she-ma'arimin she-yiskayem Torasa lilpotz yad
limlocho d'adam.
Keeping the meaning of crafty, not naked, but you scheme to find
any opportunity to learn תורה. Torah. Oh my god, I heard there's
a שיעור shiur over here, I gotta run and hear from it.
I heard that this רבי rabbi is in town, I want to
hear what he has to say. You know, you're always finding opportunities
to gather and learn at every opportunity. So you're using your, your
sort of craftiness but towards, you know, gathering as much תורה Torah
as possible. אמר רבי יוחנן אין דברי תורה מתקיימין אלא במי שמשים
עצמו כמי שאינו. amar Rabbi Yochanan ein divrei Torah miskaymin ela b'mi
she-mesim atzmo k'mi she-eino. You have to sort of make yourself like
self-negation. You have to, you know, be prepared to give up everything,
not hold, not hold by yourself compared, you know, just a hundred
percent self-sacrifice for תורה. Torah. שנאמר והחכמה she-ne'emar v'hachochma and wisdom מאין
תמצא me'ayin timatzei
will come from nothingness, I mean, literally it means where will wisdom
come from, but it means wisdom will come from nothingness. If you
make yourself like nothing, you know, that's how you'll be able to
learn תורה. Torah. Now תוספות Tosafos quotes a very important ירושלמי Yerushalmi
because it gives insight into רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's position. Let's take
a look at the, at תוספות בן עזאי אומר. Tosafos ben Azzai
omer. It says חייב אדם. chayav adam. So תוספות ירושלמי. Tosafos Yerushalmi.
דבן עזאי, d'ben Azzai, who says that a person has to
learn to teach his daughter תורה, Torah, סבר לה כרבי אלעזר בן
עזריה. savar lah k'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. דדרש הקהל את העם האנשים
והנשים והטף. d'darash hakhel es ha'am ha'anashim v'hanashim v'hatef. So, so what
is this, so this is רבי אלעזר בן עזריה'ס דרשה. Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah's drasha. So אנשים
באו ללמוד, anashim ba'u lilmod, men are coming to learn. נשים באות
לשמוע. nashim ba'os lishmoa. So that sounds like, you know, according to
בן עזאי, ben Azzai, women are also coming ללמוד. lilmod. There's an
intrinsic value in a woman's learning תורה. Torah. This makes women's learning
of תורה Torah only instrumental, לשמוע, lishmoa, not ללמוד. lilmod. What does
לשמוע lishmo'a mean if it's not for the sake of learning? ונראה
דפירוש המצוה לשמוע הנשים כדי שידעו לקיים מצוה ולא משום שיהיה לזה
זכות תורה. Venireh deperush hamitzvah lishmo'a hanashim kedei sheyeidu lekayeim mitzvah velo
mishum sheyehei lozeh zechus Torah. So you see according to this דרשה
drasha women are coming to hear. It doesn't mean that they're coming
intrinsically for the purpose of learning תורה. Torah. They're coming to learn
instruction so that they can understand how to do, how to do
the מצוות. mitzvos. So that on the one hand does not say
that there's not a value for women learning תורה, Torah, right? It's
not like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of כאילו למדה תפלות. k'ilu lamdah
tiflus. It's a middle position. Right, there's one position teach your daughter
תורה, Torah, like there's a value in learning תורה Torah for its
own sake. There's another position no, it's the worst thing possible, למדה
תפלות. lamdah tiflus. There's a middle position. It's actually good that they're
learning the מצוות mitzvos and the הלכות halachos that are relevant, but
it's not necessarily—it's not a bad—but on the other
hand it's
not an intrinsic good like תורה לשמה. Torah lishma. He contrasts it
to they're not going to הקהל Hakhel to learn in order to
know שהזכות תורה. shehazechus Torah. Be pretty funny. That's why they go
to הקהל. Hakhel. All the women come here so you could learn
this one lesson of הזכות תורה. hazechus Torah. Anyway, but presumably it
sets up like these three levels, right? That intrinsic good, essentially it's
almost a תורה Torah for its own sake in what it has
to teach you intrinsically, as a means towards קיום מצוות, kiyum mitzvos,
and the third level that it's actually a bad thing. And now
we get to the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says
it's a bad thing. So in our משנה Mishnah we only know
it's bad in the context of סוטה, Sotah, but we don't know
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has other problems with women learning תורה.
Torah. Let's take a look now as the ירושלמי Yerushalmi continues in
the first narrow line of תוספות. Tosafot. מטרונה שאלה את רבי אליעזר.
Matrona sha'alah es Rabbi Eliezer. A certain matron, a Roman woman, asked
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, מפני מה חטאו אחת במעשה העגל והן מתים
בג' מיתות. mipnei mah chata achas bama'aseh ha'egel vehen meisin begimel mitos.
There was one sin, they all were עובדי עבודה זרה, oveid avodah
zarah, but there were these different deaths, right? Some of them died
by the sword, some of them died by the מגפה, mageifah, some
of them died by drinking the water that משה Moshe made them
drink. אמר לה, Amar lah, and he refused to answer. He said
to her, אין אשה חכמה אלא בפלך, ein isha chachmah ela bapalach,
or you might have heard that, which is why the school in
Israel, the girl school, is called פלך. Pelech. It was done explicitly
ironically for this purpose. I'm serious! That's why! So it said, says,
the wisdom of a woman is only in her like what's it
called, her, her thimble, okay, only in her sewing. Women shouldn't be
learning תורה. Torah. Okay, אלא
בפלך. ela bapalach. Actually, the actual language of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is
slightly different. It's the same point. Let me see if I can
just pull it up. I had it out here before. Hold on.
בלכתך בדרך Ba'alechtecha baderech even has ירושלמי Yerushalmi on it, okay? He
says like this. He says, אמר לה אין חכמתה של אשה אלא
בפילכה.
amar lah ein chachmasah shel isha
ela bepilchah. A woman's wisdom is only in her knitting. דכתיב וכל
אשה חכמת לב בידיה
טוו. dechesiv vechol isha chachmas
lev beyadeha
tavu. What do the wise women do?
They knit. So women should just go knit. Okay, so she was
not happy with that, and this was a wealthy Roman woman. So
אמר לו הורקנוס בנו, amar lo Horkenos beno, הורקנוס Horkenos his son
said to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, בשביל שלא להשיבה דבר אחד מן
התורה, bishvil shelo le'ashivah davar echad min haTorah, you didn't want to
answer one question about the תורה, Torah, which was a completely legitimate
question, because the ירושלמי Yerushalmi goes on and says after she left,
the students said, okay, you know, you pushed her away, but it
was a good question, what's the answer? And he gave them an
answer. It was a good question! But so—it was actually a good
question—but because you refused in principle to answer a woman's question, he
says, איבדת ממנו ג' מאות כור מעשר בכל שנה. ibadta mimenu gimel
me'os kor ma'aser bechol shanah. She used to give me מעשר, ma'aser,
three hundred כור, kor, and now she's gone. You've insulted her, you
know, you've made me lose thousands of dollars because you refused to
teach her one little piece of תורה. Torah. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
he said to him, ישרפו דברי תורה ואל ימסרו דברי תורה לנשים.
yisrefu divrei Torah ve'al yimsaru divrei Torah lenashim. Better that the תורה
Torah should be burnt rather than it should be given over to
women. There actually was a book, I think by Vanessa Ochs or
whatever, anyway, by a certain woman who actually after like a year
of learning, you know, she—anyway—and how the first time she had learned
תורה Torah and how it had opened up these vistas for her.
Anyway, she wrote a book called Words on Fire and she opens
this with this quote from רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and puts the
ישרפו דברי תורה ואל ימסרו לנשים. yisrefu divrei Torah ve'al yimsaru lenashim.
So it's actually interesting, right? Here you have תורה Torah being scraped
into the water to test the woman, right? And here רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is prepared to burn תורה Torah rather than to give
it over, like the תורה Torah has to be protected, you know,
from the women. So it was not just this concern about מלמדה
תפלות. melamdah tiflus. He actually had a much—you know—he really was very
principally opposed to—maybe again, it's מלמדה תפלות, melamdah tiflus, they're going to
misuse it, they need to know their place, you know, they can't
be in the same conversation with men. So that was his position.
Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara. רבי יהושע אומר. Rabbi Yehoshua omer.
Now רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua sort of again focuses on the idea
of the women, again, as we've seen, this sort of informs this
whole discussion of סוטה, Sotah, how much is this uniquely women are
the sinners and the ones who commit adultery—although it usually takes two
to commit adultery—but anyway, you know, but completely focusing on women's sexual
sins and how much do you broaden it and say, you know,
men sin as well. As well, and is the men, is the
woman sinning because of the man? What sort of, how did he
contribute? So here in this משנה, Mishnah, in addition to this question
of teaching them תורה, Torah, it's like, oh, you're just you're going
to teach them תורה Torah because women are also always looking for
loopholes in order to find an opportunity to sin sexually, but it
obviously ties back to different attitudes in terms of how to think
about סוטה Sotah altogether. So that's what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says.
רוצה אשה בקב ותפלות, Rotze isha bekav vetiflut, a woman would rather
have one measure and the opportunity to have more sexual freedom than
to have nine measures and have more separation, more asceticism, or less
sexual freedom. So מאי קאמר, mai qamar, what's he saying? הכי קאמר.
hachi qamar. רוצה אשה בקב ותפלות עמה, Rotze isha bekav vetiflut imah,
a woman would rather have one measure and the ability to have
greater sort of sexual opportunity מתשעה קבין ופרישות, mitisha kabim uprishut, nine
measures without it. Now what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi explains,
if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, two three lines down
in the narrow lines. רוצה אשה בקב ותפלות, Rotze isha bekav vetiflut,
חפצה ליזון במזונות מועטין, chafetza lizon bimzonot muatin, she'd rather that her
husband not
go out, have a
more modest
income, and her sexual desire again is, and what's the bad? I
mean it's a woman who wants to be with her husband, like
why is that seen as something bad, right? That's also very strange.
Like עונתה לא יגרע, onatah lo yigra, and we're supposed to talk
about the value of marital sex and so on, and here it's
all being cast as a negative. She wants to be with her
husband. She'd rather her husband get a lower paying job and be
home more often so she could be with him more, right? מתשעה
קבין ופרישות, mitisha kabim uprishut, where were we? I skipped a line.
מתשעה קבין ופרישות, mitisha kabim uprishut, לפרוש מן התפלות, lifrosh min hatiflut,
ובכך אין טוב שתלמד תורה, ubechach ein tov shetilmad Torah, therefore because
obviously it'll sort of set them off the path. But anyway, the
point being that because then it'll teach her how to cheat also.
But the bottom point is, I mean תוספות Tosafot explains it more
clearly. Look at תוספות, Tosafot, maybe in רש"י Rashi it wasn't so
much about her husband. I was actually, רש"י Rashi just says she'd
rather have greater sexual freedom. But תוספות Tosafot explains it about her
husband. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. רוצה אשה בקב ותפלות, Rotze isha bekav
vetiflut, פירוש רבינו חננאל. perush Rabbeinu Chananel. רוצה אשה שיהיה בעלה חמר,
Rotze isha sheyehei baalah chammar, he should be a donkey driver,
and he should be home more often. He's home every שבת Shabbat
so she's able to be together with him once a week, לתת
לה עונתה, latet lah onatah, to have marital sex, ולא יביא
לה אלא קב חטים בלבד, velo yavi lah ella kav chitim bilvad,
and he earns a meager income. ולא יהיה גמל, Velo yehei gammal,
he'd rather he be that than he be a גמל, gammal, camel
driver, שהולך בדרך רחוקה, sheholech bederech rechoka, that he goes far away
on long trips, ואינו עושה לה עונה אלא אחת לששים יום, ve'eino
oseh lo onah ella achat lishishim yom, and he's only home once
a month. ואף על פי שמביא לה לשכרה תשעה קבין, ve'af al
pi shemavi lo lischaro tisha kabim, and even though he'd make a
lot bigger income that way, חביבה עליה עונה בכל שבת, chaviva aleiha
onah bechol Shabbat, she'd much rather have him present every week and
every שבת, Shabbat, וקב אחד מתשעה קבין ופרישות ל' יום. vekav echad
mitisha kabim uprishut lamed yom. Okay, which is, that seems lovely! What's
the matter with that? And I would think that husbands also should
feel that way, right? So
it's very strange. I mean רש"י Rashi didn't say it's about husband
and wife, he just said in general. But here, okay, why is
that being cast as a negative is not at all clear. And
that's why it's a danger to teach her תורה Torah because then
she's going to be looking with sex with another man. What? Anyway,
alright. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. הוא היה אומר, Hu hayah
omer, חסיד שוטה. chasid shoteh. He'd say a stupid חסיד, chasid, a
stupid righteous person,
and a whole list, we're going to do חסיד שוטה chasid shoteh
right now. Oh, we're going to do two. He said a חסיד
שוטה, chasid shoteh, a stupid righteous person, ורשע ערום, verasha arum, and
a crafty wicked person, ואשה פרושה, ve'isha perusha, and a woman who
is ascetic, which presumably means that he thinks that it's all a
fake, that women won't really choose that, she pretends to be, ומכות
פרושים, umakkot perushim, and sort of people that are these
self-flagellating ascetics, which he also thinks is like a false type of
righteousness, they destroy the world. I'm sorry, what'd you say?
They all walked into a bar.
Alright, they all walk into a bar, exactly. Okay. So what's a
חסיד שוטה? chasid shoteh?
So rabbi and a priest and a minister walk into a bar
and the bartender says, "What is this, a
joke?" Okay. Anyway, חסיד שוטה. chasid shoteh. היכי דמי חסיד שוטה? Hechei
dami chasid shoteh? What's a חסיד שוטה? chasid shoteh? כגון דקא טבעא
איתתא בנהרא, Kegon deka taveia itta benahra, a
woman is drowning in the river, ואמר לאו אורח ארעא לאיסתכולי בה,
ve'amar lav orach ara listakulei bah, it's forbidden to look at women,
ואצולה, ve'atzulah, and to save her.
So sadly there are people who would react that way. תוספות Tosafot
has another version of it, actually this is very nice because this
actually shows about like it's around the whole sexual issue and about
not being too פרום, frum, like in a way that actually ignores
real lives and issues that are going on. Anyway, take a look
at תוספות. Tosafot. היכי דמי חסיד שוטה? Hechei dami chasid shoteh? ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. ראה תינוק מבעבע בנהרא, Ra'ah tinok meva'be'a benahra,
so an infant drowning.
אמר לכשאחלוץ תפילין אצילנו. Amar lichshe'echlotz tefillin atzilennu. Wait, I gotta take
off my תפילין, tefillin, I gotta finish שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei first.
Okay, עד שיחלוץ תפילין יצאה נשמתו. ad shecholeitz tefillin yatzah nishmato. הוציא
זה נפשו. hotzi zeh nafsho. While you're busy now finishing up your
דאוונען davening and taking off your תפילין, tefillin, this guy is drowned.
Very nice pun, the אחלוץ echlotz and תפילין. tefillin. Oh, I didn't
get that.
That's cute, I didn't think about that. Yeah.
Why should she take... תפלות? tiflus? What is the source of that
word? In other words, it's bothered me for years to get at
the really... like the משנה Mishna juxtaposes תפלות tiflus to
שטות. shtis. In other words, if she learns תורה, Torah, she's turning
it just into dirty water? Like that's a very limited like... What's
the word?
Yeah, I don't know. Yeah, me neither. Yeah, okay. All right, you
can do research and come back to us tomorrow. Amravya says, okay,
so that was חסיד שוטה. chasid shoteh. We could have a lot
of fun thinking up other versions of חסיד שוטה. chasid shoteh. But
now we get to היכי דמי רשע ערום, heichy dami rasha arum,
which is interesting because, like what do you mean a רשע ערום?
rasha arum? Anybody that's, you know, wicked and is also crafty, but
apparently the idea is is that the craftiness because of the whole
מבלי עולם, mavlei olam, the problem of מבלי עולם mavlei olam is
that they're not exactly what they seem. Person seems to be oh
I'm so פרום, frum, but your פרום קייט frumkeit comes at the
expense of of... it's not real righteousness, it comes at the expense
of other people. Oh you appear to be, you know, such a
צדיק tzaddik that you're constantly self-flagellating, but that's not real צדקות, tzidkus,
right? You appear to be this woman appears to be a פרושה
prusha but she's not really a פרושה. prusha. So a רשע ערום
rasha arum presumably is somebody who who does his רשעות rishus בערמימות.
be'armimus. Like he does his רשעות rishus with craftiness so it's not
clear to people that he's really a רשע. rasha. Yeah, okay. And
that seems to be the issue of the רשע ערום. rasha arum.
So let's... yeah but let's see what this רשע ערום rasha arum
is. רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, זה המטעים דבריו לדיין קודם שיבוא בעל
דין חבירו. zeh hamatin devarav ledayan kodem sheba ba'al din chaveiro. You
actually, he actually like you know he comes he comes early to
the court case and he starts telling to the judge what the
case is. So what that does is that even if the judge
thinks, oh I'm going to be impartial, once the case issue has
been framed in a particular way, it's very hard to shift your
paradigm and to appreciate the other way in which you know the
other version of events, right? You've already started fundamentally with this version
of the events. And that's a real problem. There's actually a לאו
lav of hearing one of the בעלי דין ba'alei din before the
other one is present. And it really does bias you.
Okay. רבי אבהו אומר, Rabbi Avohu omer, so anyway but what did
I do? Ah I didn't I didn't lie, I didn't bribe, I
just got started you know you were a few minutes late, I
was a few minutes early, I just got started. So it's very
you know very subtle but very you know very impactful.
Okay. רבי אבהו אומר זה הנותן דינר לעני להשלים לו מאתיים זוז.
Rabbi Avohu omer zeh nosein dinar le'ani lehashlim lo masayim zuz. That
you actually, oh I'm going to be a צדיק tzaddik I'll give
this עני ani I'll give him a dollar. Now the thing was
was that he had 199 זוז zuz which technically put him under
the line of poverty, okay, under the poverty line which means that
he is
entitled to פאה לקט peah leket etc. he's considered an עני. ani.
Once you gave him this one dollar he's no longer an עני,
ani, he's not entitled. Sort of like somebody who makes just enough
not to be eligible for financial aid but not enough to actually
afford what college costs. Okay? So you actually gave this person just
enough to make them no longer eligible for מתנות עניים. matnas aniyim.
I gave the guy a you know I was nice to him
I gave him a ten buck, okay but...
actually the year where it's...
no he actually has either מאתיים זוז masayim zuz in you know
like currently as his assets or חמישים זוז fifty zuz invested. Either
way that's considered to be not an עני. ani. דתנן, detnan, מי
שיש לו מאתיים זוז, mi sheyeish lo masayim zuz, if somebody has
200 זוז, zuz, לא יטול לקט שכחה ופאה. lo yitol leket shichecha
peah. He cannot take מתנות עניים matnas aniyim because he's already not
considered an עני. ani. ומעשר עני. umaaser ani. היה לו מאתיים חסר
דינר, hayah lo masayim chaser dinar, if he was missing one דינר
dinar short, אפילו אלף נותנין לו כאחת. afilu elef nosnin lo ke'achas.
You can give him at that moment he's an עני ani and
you can give him ten thousand dollars worth of you know of
פאה peah or מעשר עני. maaser ani. Okay, אחרי acharei after he
takes it he can't take any more but that one thing you
can give him because at that moment of that exchange he was
an עני. ani. הרי זה יטול. harei zeh yitol. רב אסי, Rav
Assi, so anyway but what you did is here he was coming
knocking at your door for מעשר עני maaser ani and you actually
before you say you know what before I give you the מעשר
עני maaser ani here you know just take this twenty bucks okay
I want to consider... oh too bad now I can't give you
מעשר עני. maaser ani. Okay. רב אסי אמר, Rav Assi amar, oh
I don't get the point you have to eventually give מעשר עני
maaser ani to someone but whatever.
In the case of פאה peah or לקט leket and sell it
and turn it into merchandise? He can.
He can? Yeah sure. Okay. רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן זה המשיא
עצה למכור בנכסים מועטים. Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan zeh masi eitza
limkor binchasim mu'atim. You give advice to somebody to sell when there's
a small estate. What does this mean? דאמר רבי יוסי אמר רבי
יוחנן יתומים שקדמו ומכרו בנכסים מועטים מה שמכרו מכרו. de'amar Rabbi Yosei
amar Rabbi Yochanan yesomim shekadmu umachru binchasim mu'atim mah shemachru machru. If
it's a small estate then the male heirs do not actually inherit
anything because all of the estate is earmarked to support the... their
sisters in terms of מזונות. mezonos. So you know because the sisters
are right have a lien on the estate and a right to
be supported until they basically get married. But the thing is is
that if the male heirs go ahead and sell off the estate
then
then the sisters only have a lien on the real estate that
was inherited. If it was actually sold and
and liquidated the
sisters don't have... You're just giving the boys some advice, you know?
And actually תוספות Tosafot says, and actually, it might not be wrong
for the boy for the sons to do that. But what's wrong
is for you who doesn't have any any like horse in the
race, you know, you don't have a stake in it, and you're
just coming in and hurting some people to the benefit of others.
Okay? אביי אמר זה משיא עצה למכור בנכסים כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל.
Abaye amar ze masi etza limkor binchasim k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. Let's
just read this last line. That you give advice, again, advice that
unsolicited advice that hurts some people, helps others like רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. Oh, to sell to sell the the property. What is this?
דתניא. Detanya. נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני. Nichasai l'cha v'achareiha l'ploni. If you
say, I'm going to give all of my my my property to
Shimon, and after Shimon dies, it'll it should go over to I
mean, I'll give it all to Reuven and after Reuven dies, it'll
go over to Shimon. ירד ראשון ומכר ואכל. Yarad rishon umachar v'achal.
And the first one went down and he sold off the property
that you gave him. השני מוציא מיד הלקוחות. Hasheini motzi miyad halakuchot.
So the second guy, once Reuven dies, can take the property back
from whoever purchased it from Reuven, because it's coming to him. דברי
רבי. Divrei Rabbi. That's what Rabbi says. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
אין לשני אלא מה ששייר ראשון. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer ein
lasheini ela ma sheshiyer rishon. No, the second guy gets only what
Reuven actually left over. But if Reuven sold it, it only goes
straight from Reuven to Shimon. If Reuven sold it in his life,
Shimon never gets it. So you go and you tell Reuven and
you say, hey, you know what, if you want to keep this
in your, you know, you want to keep this proper the the
value of this property and pass it onto your kids, you should
sell it and you can pass on the proceeds to your kids
and then it won't go over to Shimon. So you're sort of,
you know, you are subverting the intent of the original person who
gave it, but you know, you're just, what do you want from
me? I'm just giving Reuven some good financial advice. But presumably, again,
תוספות Tosafot says it wouldn't be wrong for Reuven to do this,
but it's wrong for you to do it just סתם stam hurt
one person and subvert the intent without having a particular stake. And
again, if he hired you as his financial planner, maybe it wouldn't
be. But in this case, it's considered as as inappropriate. Okay. And
I guess we'll end here, we'll pick up with more רשע ערום,
rasha arum, there's two more examples, but we but not to rush,
we'll pick up with that tomorrow. Okay. All disappointed.